创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets of a place we call "The Universe."
环抱在银河系气体尘埃的旋臂中
Among the swirling gas and dust in the arms of the Milky Way,
繁星闪现 并不孤单 而是成群结队
stars flash into existence, not alone, but in clusters,
靠引力结合在一起
held together by the force of gravity.
引力就像是宇宙中的雕塑家
Gravity is like the sculptor of the universe.
现在来一次星系中的星团大巡游
Now take a grand tour of the galaxy's star clusters,
太空宝藏图
the treasure maps of space,
掌握着银河系里4000亿颗太阳奥秘的关键线索
holding critical clues to the mysteries of the Milky Way's 400 billion suns.
星团确实让我们掌握了
Star clusters really allowed us to get a handle
恒星是如何度过一生的 以及它们的生死情况
on how stars go through their lives, how they live and die.
那是暴戾混乱的世界 我们搜寻宇宙星团
It's a violent, chaotic existence, where our search for cosmic clusters
可能最终揭示一个永恒暗无天日的宇宙
may end up revealing a universe in darkness for eternity.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第7集 搜寻宇宙星团
The History Channel - The Universe s04e07 The Search For Cosmic Clusters
在地球的夜晚 有上千颗恒星是肉眼可见的
About a thousand stars are visible to the naked eye during a dark night on planet Earth.
星光闪烁给我们留下了深刻印象
While the glistening display may impress us,
但是星系中到处是令我们吃惊的景象
there are places in the galaxy where the view would blow us away.
试想一下处在百万颗恒星组成的大星团边缘的太阳
Imagine the Sun on the edge of a giant cluster made up of a million other suns,
撑满了天空 从地平线到地平线
filling the heavens horizon to horizon.
星际密度实在是高
The stellar density is really high.
恒星间的距离
The distances between stars
可能就是百分之几光年的样子
can be just a few hundredths of a light-year, something like that.
星系间华丽的星团
The galaxy's magnificent clusters
远不止外表的美丽
are more than just beautiful to look at.
你可能还未意识到
You may not realize it,
但是它们掌握着恒星诞生的秘密
but they hold the very secrets to the way stars are created
以及它们是如何毁于
and how they're destroyed in
产生生命关键元素的超新星爆发的
massive supernova explosions that generate the very elements of life.
我们开始搜索宇宙星团
Our search for cosmic clusters begins
并不是通过望远镜的目镜
not through the eyepiece of a telescope,
而是在星际飞船的座舱里
but in the cockpit of an interstellar spacecraft.
我们的任务是 穿行星系
Our mission: to traverse the galaxy
查明星团为何如此珍贵
and find out why clusters are so valuable,
它们为什么是解开恒星奥秘的关键
why they are keys to unlocking the mysteries of the stars.
我们的第一站 昴星团 所有星团中最著名的
Our first stop, the Pleiades, the most famous star cluster of all,
距离地球440光年
440 light-years from Earth.
自古以来广为人知 它包括了上千颗恒星
Known since antiquity, it contains a thousand stars,
尽管只有少数能在地球上看到
though only a handful can be seen from Earth.
昴星团就是所谓的七姐妹
The Pleiades are the so-called Seven Sisters,
明亮 在秋天的星空里很容易辨认出的星团
a bright, easily noticeable grouping of stars in the winter skies.
原来只有六颗星星显而易见
Well, it turns out only six of the stars are easily visible.
你可以看到六颗 眼尖者
You can see six, and really sharp-eyed people
可以看到8颗 9颗 甚至10颗星
can see eight or nine or ten.
我遇到的人难得有可以准确看到7颗星的
Rarely have I met anyone who can see precisely seven stars.
也许在古代 有一颗星
So maybe in antiquity, there was a star
亮度远远超过它现在的亮度
that was considerably brighter than it is now,
但是打那时起它已经消失了
but it has faded since then,
因此现在只有六颗星显而易见
so now there are only six easily visible stars.
昂星团里有数百颗恒星
There are actually hundreds of stars in the Pleiades,
或许有上千颗
perhaps up to a thousand.
我们围绕着昂星团搜索线索
We circle the Pleiades in search of clues
可以揭示宇宙的秘密
that can reveal the secrets of the universe,
因为星团里掌握着了解恒星如何诞生
because clusters hold the key to understanding
它们的生死情况以及创世之谜的关键
how stars are born, how they live and die, the secrets of creation.
和所有的星团一样 我们看到昂星团里的群星
Like all clusters, we see that the stars in the Pleiades
相互挨得很近
are so close to each other,
它们与地球的距离大差不离
they are all virtually the same distance from Earth.
当然啦 星团里的恒星
Of course, the stars in a cluster
与我们的距离并不是完全相同的
are not all exactly at the same distance from us,
但是它们非常遥远 距离上的细微差别
but they're so far away that the slight differences in distance
确实很小
are really pretty small.
那是无关紧要的
They're inconsequential.
恰当的比喻就是在从高空飞艇上
A nice analogy is viewing a stadium full of people
观察坐满观众的体育场
from a blimp high above.
从飞艇上远眺
From the perspective of the blimp,
大部分人都处在相同的距离上
most of the people are at about the same distance.
我们对群星所了解的大部分情况 -
Most of what we know about stars--
个头 重量 年龄 -
their size, weight, and age--
都来自对它们内在亮度的计算
comes from figuring out their inherent brightness.
但是你不知道恒星的距离的话
But you can't judge a star's true brightness
是无法判断其真实亮度的
without knowing how far away it is.
那里就是星团出现的地方
That's where the cluster comes in.
事实上 星团里所有的星星
The fact that all stars in a star cluster
与我们的距离基本相同是非常重要的
are basically the same distance from us is very important.
它给了我们一个恒星的样本 我们实际上可以看到
It gives us a sample of stars where we can actually see
那些恒星真正的内在亮度
what the intrinsic real brightness of these stars are.
除非我们知道这些恒星都处在同一个位置
Unless we know these stars are all at the same location,
否则我们就不知道我们是否看到的亮星较远
we don't know whether we're looking at a bright star that's far away
而较暗的星则离我们较近 是没有办法明白的
or a dimmer star that's close to us. There's no way to tell.
但是在星团里 都在一起 你就可以看个明白
But in a cluster, all together, you can see that.
适合天上群星的规则
The same rules that apply to stars in the sky
同样也适合于道路上的汽车
also apply to cars on the road.
我们这里有两辆汽车 同一个牌子 同一个型号
What we have here are two cars-- same make, same model--
所以我们知道两辆车的前灯是一模一样的
so we know the headlights on each car are exactly alike
亮度也是一样的
and equally bright.
从我现在所处的位置
From where I'm standing here,
一辆车的前灯看上去与另外一辆并无两样
one car's headlights look just like the other.
那是合乎情理的
That makes sense.
现在让我们让这些车子来模拟一下宇宙中的恒星 -
But now let's make these cars act like stars in the universe--
同样的恒星 但处在不同的距离上
same stars, but at different distances.
好 艾米 倒车
Okay, Amy, back it up.
现在来看看这些前灯
Look at these headlights now.
那边的灯要比这里的灯暗很多
The ones over there are much dimmer than the ones here,
虽然我们知道它们是一样的
even though we know they're the same.
这就是平方反比定律
This is the inverse square law.
如果汽车的距离增加一倍
If that car is twice as far away,
那么前灯的亮度就会暗上四倍
then the headlights are four times dimmer.
如果距离远四倍 前灯就会暗上16倍
If it's four times farther away, the headlights are 16 times dimmer,
以此类推 随你走多远
and so on as far as you care to go.
不过有时灯光会看上去比实际的更暗
But sometimes a light that appears to be dimmer actually is.
这手电筒和前灯
This flashlight and the headlights
就像是星团里的恒星
are just like stars in a star cluster.
手电筒靠近前灯 看上去较暗
The flashlight next to the headlight looks dimmer,
那是因为它较暗 而不是因为它较远
and that's because it is dimmer, not because it's farther away.
星团里亮星旁边的暗星看上去较暗
A dim star next to a bright star in a cluster looks dimmer
那是因为该星本身较暗 而不是因为它较远
because the star itself is dimmer, not because it's farther away.
我们靠近看的话 昂星团里交杂着亮星和暗星
Up close, we see the Pleiades has a mix of bright stars and dim stars,
星团里有各种各样的恒星
and it's this very variety of different stars in a cluster,
都处在相同的地方
all in the same place,
这就解决了恒星演化的难题
that solves the puzzle of stellar evolution.
星团确实让我们掌握了
Star clusters really allowed us to get a handle
恒星是如何度过一生的 以及它们的生死情况
on how stars go through their lives, how they live and die.
这样来考虑它 -
Think of it this way--
如果有外星人想了解人类的生死情况
if an alien wanted to learn how humans live and die,
但是他们只能观察我们30秒 -
but they could only watch us for 30 seconds--
他们飞经地球拍到了数百万人的照片 -
they flew by Earth and they took pictures of millions of humans--
虽然他们并没有观察到某一个人的生与死
even though they couldn't watch a single human live and die,
作为群体 他们就可以拼凑出我们的故事了
as a group, they could piece together our story.
他们看到了一些婴儿 看到了老人
They looked at some babies, they looked at older people.
星团就是那样
A star cluster is just that.
这是一张同时快照
It's a single snapshot in time.
然而群星都处在生命的不同阶段
But there are stars at every different part of their lives,
那就是天文学家所需的工具
and that was the tool astronomers needed
来拼凑出恒星一生的情况
to piece together what a stellar lifetime is like.
我们知道最大最亮的恒星
We know that the biggest, brightest stars
是最危险的 所以我们要保持距离
are the most dangerous, so we keep our distance.
这些都是宇宙间生活艰辛 英年早逝的恒星
These are the live-hard, die-young stars of the universe,
它们膨胀到巨大的个头 随后变成了超新星
those that expand to giant size before going supernova.
威胁潜伏在星团里
The dangers lurk even in clusters
具有诱人的名字 如珠宝盒
with appealing names, like the Jewel Box.
我们行程的下一站要去的地方
But the next stop on our journey is a place in the sky
是北半球人非常熟悉的
very familiar to people in the northern hemisphere.
我们距离地球80光年
We are 80 light-years from Earth,
来到了离我们最近的星团
approaching the closest cluster to our planet,
大熊座移动星群
the Ursa Major Moving Group.
我们带着我们的飞船四处转悠
As we bring our starship around,
我们看到大熊座中间的的五颗恒星
we see five of the central stars in Ursa Major
构成了我们所谓的北斗七星
form what we know as the Big Dipper.
人们注意到它们实际上是一起在天上移动
People noticed that they actually move across the sky together.
大多数星座里的群星 虽然它们看上去
With most constellations, the stars, even though they look
像是属于同一个星座
like they're part of the same constellation,
但是它们其实是风马牛不相干的
they're actually completely unrelated to each other.
它们相互之间毫无引力关系
They have nothing to do with each other gravitationally.
然而大熊座移动星群里的恒星
However, the stars in the Ursa Major Moving Group
实际上是同时形成的 属于同一个移动星群
actually formed at the same time and are part of the same moving group.
随着时间的推移 运动会改变
In time, the movement will change the appearance
群星熟悉的模样
of the familiar pattern of stars.
我们拜访大熊座去探索另一个星团问题
We're visiting Ursa Major to explore another cluster question:
为什么有些星团会比其它的更加分散？
why are some more spread out than others?
不规则的形状 疏散的外貌
Irregular in shape and scattered in appearance,
它们被称为疏散星团
they're called open clusters.
疏散星团是相对松散的恒星集群
An open star cluster is a relatively loosely bound aggregation of stars.
它们形成于螺旋星系的旋臂里
They form in the spiral arms of a spiral galaxy
于是它们渐行渐远 散开了
and then they gradually move away, and then they disperse.
科学家认为几乎所有的恒星都诞生于星团里
Scientists believe virtually all stars are born in clusters,
但是随着时间的推移
but as time goes on,
疏散星团中的恒星在其它路过的恒星的
the stars in open clusters get scattered apart
引力作用下拆散了
by the gravity of other passing stars.
那意味着大部分星团是年轻的
That means most clusters are young
因为 要不然 其中的恒星早已不在星团里了
because, otherwise, their stars would no longer be in clusters.
星团就像是我手里的这团五彩纸屑
A star cluster is kind of like this pile of confetti on my hand.
引力逐渐将群星拉开 把星团分开
Gravity gradually pulls the stars away and disperses the cluster.
好 我可以吹这团五彩纸屑 将纸团吹散
Well, I can blow on this pile of confetti and disperse the pile.
这就来吹
Let's do it.
现在如果这里是个星团而不是五彩纸屑团
Now if this were a star cluster instead of a pile of confetti,
那么引力就是逐渐将恒星拉开的原动力
then gravity would be the agent that gradually pulls the stars away,
随着时间的推移逐渐拆散星团直到一点点 如果有东西留下的话
dispersing the cluster over time until there is little, if anything, left.
作为探险家 这些年轻的星团对我们非常重要
As explorers, these young clusters are important to us.
由于有好多恒星在一个地方 就好象我们可以开展一项民意调查
With a lot of stars in one place, it's as if we can take a poll
搞明白星系里的各种恒星有多普遍或稀有
and figure out how common or rare different kinds of stars are in the galaxy.
在大部分星团里 我们一下子就看到有一些很大很亮的恒星
In most clusters, we see quickly that there are a few very big, bright stars,
或许还有大量的像我们的太阳那样的普通恒星
maybe a larger number of ordinary stars like our Sun,
很多很多昏暗的小恒星 挤在一起几乎难以分辨
and lots and lots of small, dim stars, barely visible in the crowd.
那么它们有多拥挤呢？
But how crowded are they really?
星团里的恒星都相距几十亿英里
Stars in clusters are many billions of miles apart.
但是我们一旦将它们的距离输入我们飞船上的计算机
But when we add up their distances in our starship computer,
我们发现它们靠在一起超过了我们过去的认为
we find they're much closer together than we're used to at home.
太阳所在的街区里 恒星密度
The density of stars in the Sun's neighborhood
差不多是每50立方光年里一颗恒星
is little more than one star for every 50 cubic light-years.
在典型的疏散星团里
In a typical open cluster,
同样的空间里会有500颗恒星
there would be 500 stars in the same space.
我们曾经在一个疏散星团里
We were once in an open cluster,
但是我们已经围绕着星系N多圈了
but we've been around the galaxy so many times now
现在我们的姐妹恒星都可能
that our sister stars may be
到了银河系的另外一面了
all the way on the other side of the Milky Way.
当年太阳作为星团的一部分会是何种模样呢？
What would it have been like for the Sun when it was part of a cluster?
为了找到答案 我们提出了一个飞行计划
To find out, we file a flight plan
寻找有恒星现在正在星团里形成的地方
for a place where stars are forming in a cluster right now.
我们前行1500光年 从地球前往猎户座星云
We're headed 1,500 light-years from Earth to the Orion Nebula,
那里看上去好像猎户的宝剑里有一颗模糊的恒星
which looks like a fuzzy star in Orion's sword.
凑近一看 居然是一个壮观的星光秀
Up close, though, it's a spectacular light show.
猎户座星云是著名的星际托儿所之一
The Orion Nebula is one of the great stellar nurseries that we know of.
现在正在形成恒星
It's forming stars right now,
如果你飞经猎户座星云
and if you were to fly through the Orion Nebula,
你会看到一大堆恒星
you would see a whole bunch of stars.
然而靠近中央 有四颗特别明亮的恒星
But near the middle, there are four particularly bright stars.
它们构成的形状叫做猎户座四边形
They form a configuration called the Trapezium,
如果你飞经这些恒星
and if you were to fly past these stars,
你会看到这四颗新形成的明亮的恒星
you would see these four newly formed brilliant stars
以及一大堆小家伙漂浮在四周
and a whole bunch of little guys all floating around.
那是一个美妙的旅程
It would be a wonderful journey.
我们朝四边形恒星而去
We head toward the Trapezium stars,
星团里四颗最亮的星是最忙碌的恒星形成实验室
the four brightest in a cluster that's a hectic laboratory of star formation.
成千上万颗恒星已经形成或正在形成
Thousands of other stars have formed or are in the process of forming,
但是随之而来的是 科学家认为星团
but as it's happening, scientists believe the cluster is imposing
正对整个循环施加着某种生育控制
a kind of birth control on the whole cycle.
只有约10%的云量会形成恒星
Only about 10% of the mass of a cloud which will form stars
实际成为恒星
actually become stars.
那么为什么星云中就这么一点物质
So why is it that so little of the matter in a cloud
真正变成恒星呢？
actually turns into stars?
我们现在已经开始相信可能存在着一个反馈过程
What we've come to believe now is that there may be a feedback process.
所以你一旦形成了恒星 它们就会反过来对星云有所作用
So once you form stars, they feed back on the cloud,
就像调节器一样 实际上限制了
acting like a thermostat and actually limiting
可形成的恒星的形成量
the amount of star formation that can form.
在四边形星团里 你看到那四颗大质量恒星
In the Trapezium Cluster, you've got those 4 massive stars
正大量产生着紫外线辐射
that are producing enormous amount of ultraviolet radiation,
以及恒星风射入周围的区域
as well as winds that stream into the surrounding area.
它们会影响到那些想形成恒星的气体
And they will affect the gas that wants to form stars.
因此即使你再有1000颗恒星
So even though you have another thousand stars
在四边形周围形成
forming around the Trapezium,
那个区域里的恒星形成率也经受着
the star-formation rate in that area is being affected
那些大质量恒星的紫外线以及恒星风的影响
by the ultraviolet radiation and the winds from those massive stars.
如果星云是宇宙恒星托儿所的话
If nebulas are the stellar nurseries of the cosmos,
那么星团就是它们的小学了
then clusters are their grade schools,
在那里 群星呆在一起直至终身或星系将它们驱散
where stars stay together until life and the galaxy drives them apart.
然而很显然 并非所有的星团都是一样的
But it's clear, not all clusters are alike.
我们现在由于所遇到的星团
We're due now to encounter clusters
构成了整个星系里最极端的环境
that make up some of the most extreme environments in the entire galaxy,
其中恒星非常庞大 它们正处在
where stars are so massive, they are on the verge
自我爆发让人遗忘的边缘
of blasting themselves into oblivion.
说起星团
When it comes to star clusters,
多数人想知道的一个关键问题是
one of the first things most people want to know is,
谁为最大？
what's the biggest?
哪些尤为突出？
Which ones really stand out?
这与观察大城市并无差异
It's no different than looking at a big city.
你想知道其中最高的建筑
You want to know about its tallest buildings,
最鲜明的地标
its most distinctive landmarks.
如果有星团中的帝国大厦的话
If there's an Empire State Building of star clusters,
我们就不得不走上1万光年去寻找它
we'd have to travel 10,000 light-years to find it.
它叫做韦斯特伦德1(Westerlund 1)
It's called Westerlund 1,
一个总质量是我们太阳10万倍的超级星团
a supercluster with a total mass 100,000 times our Sun.
韦斯特伦德1目前保持着最大的
Westerlund 1 right now holds the world's record
已知年轻星团的世界纪录
for the biggest known young cluster.
它拥有约10万颗恒星 其怪异之处
It has about 100,000 stars, and what's really odd
就是很长时期里 我们居然不知道它有那么庞大
is for a long time we didn't even know it was that massive.
天文学家知道韦斯特伦德1有好长时间了
Astronomers have known about Westerlund 1 for a long time,
然而只是在5年前
but only about five years ago,
我们才真正第一次大致了解到这个星团里所有的恒星
did we first get a glimpse of all the stars in the cluster,
因为当时我们有了红外探测器
because that's when we had infrared detectors
能够透过地球与
that could peer through
该星团之间的星系里的尘埃
the dust in the galaxy that's situated between the Earth and the cluster.
红外天文学上的最新进展
Recent advances in infrared astronomy
揭示了一个只有6光年宽的空间
revealed a space only six light-years across,
充满了众多恒星
packed with a thick population of stars.
最大最亮的是银河怪物
The biggest and brightest are galactic freaks,
超巨星有一系列的大小和颜色
supergiant stars in a range of sizes and colors,
从蓝色到红色甚至黄色
from blue to red and even yellow.
蓝色超巨星阶段
The blue supergiant phase
以及黄色 红色的超巨星阶段
and the yellow and red supergiant phase
代表了大质量恒星生命里的各个阶段
represent phases during the lifetime of a massive star.
它们始于蓝色 然后变成红色
They start blue, they become red.
在某种情况下 它们来回折腾于
In some cases they go back and forth
蓝红之间 因为其外层升起后
between blue and red as the outer layers are lifted
我们看到了深处温度较高的物质
and we see deeper to the hotter material.
介于红蓝阶段之间 它们是黄色的
In between the red and the blue phases, they're yellow.
因此我们称其为黄巨星
And so we call them yellow supergiants.
太阳 之所以通常被称为普通恒星
The Sun, which so often is called an ordinary star,
是因为相对各种颜色的超巨星是很小的
is tiny when compared to supergiants of any color.
假设我们的太阳
Suppose our Sun,
它超过地球直径100倍
which is over a hundred times the diameter of the Earth,
缩小到这个黄色针头那么大
were scaled down to the size of this little yellow pinhead here,
直径小于1/8英寸
less than 1/8 inch in diameter.
那么我们真的大大缩小了太阳
So we're really scaling down the Sun a lot.
如果那样 最大的恒星 红巨星
In that case, the largest stars, the red supergiants,
就会是我身后的望远镜穹顶那般大
would be about the size of this telescope dome behind me.
它们相对太阳非常大
They're huge compared with the Sun,
然而太阳本身相对地球就已经够大的了
and yet the Sun itself is already huge compared with the Earth.
超巨星 不管是蓝 黄 还是红
Supergiant stars, whether blue, yellow, or red,
统称为变体巨星
are collectively called evolved massive stars.
这意味着它们耗尽了它们的核氢燃料
That means they've burnt out their nuclear hydrogen fuel
正在变成巨星 有可能最终会成为超新星爆发
and are transforming into giants that may eventually explode as supernovas.
超新星非常明亮 很远处都不难看到它们
Supernovas are so bright, it's easy to see them from great distances.
然而 来自宾州的大卫有个问题问《宇宙》节目 -
But David Y. from Wing, Pennsylvania, wants to
超新星是否会扭曲时空到足以让我们注意到变化呢？
ask "The Universe" if supernova can cause space and time to warp enough to make us notice to change?
大卫 我们当然希望超新星
David, we sure hope that a supernova
会引起足够大的干扰
will create a big enough disturbance,
扭曲时空 显而易见
a warping in space and time, to be noticeable,
不过它不会轻易显现的
but it won't be easily noticeable.
你不会被搅乎到
You won't be jostled around.
不过我们希望当前和未来一代的
But we hope that the current and future generation
引力波探测器会探测到时空结构中的
of gravitational wave detectors will detect these slight ripples
这些细微的涟漪
in the fabric of space and time.
那是新的尚未探测的天体物理学的窗口
That's the new unexplored window of astrophysics,
引力波天文学
gravitational wave astronomy.
我们的太阳也将演化成红巨星
Our own Sun will evolve into a red giant.
它将膨胀到足以吞没地球的轨道
It will expand enough to engulf Earth's orbit,
但是它不会像超巨星那样的规模到达木星的轨道
but it won't reach the size of Jupiter's orbit like supergiants,
它不会以超新星爆发
and it won't explode in a supernova.
星团里具有超巨星给了我们该星团年龄的线索
Having supergiants in a cluster gives us clues to the cluster's age.
现在那些庞大的巨星意义非凡
Now, those incredibly massive stars are important
因为它们的寿命很短
because they have very short lives.
它们只能活约500到600万年
They only live for maybe 5 or 6 million years.
如果你看到恒星 经过演化的巨星
So if you see a star, a massive star that's evolved,
那已经接近其生命的结束
that's near the end of its life,
你要知道星团不可能活过500到600万岁的
you know that the cluster can't be more than 5 or 6 million years old
因为到了那时 巨星都已经炸毁了
'cause if it were, that massive star would already have blown up.
至今为止 天文学家发现
To date, astronomers have discovered
只有少数这样的超大规模星团
only a handful of these extremely massive clusters,
如韦斯特伦德1
and like Westerlund 1,
它们都几乎不为人知 直到最近
all of them were virtually unknown until very recently.
就来看看我们有多无知
Just to express how ignorant we are,
就是在10年前
realize that only 10 years ago,
我们对这些大规模星团一无所知
we didn't know about any of these massive clusters.
我们在10年前所知的所有年轻的星团
Every young cluster we knew about more than 10 years ago,
都不足一万颗恒星
all had less than 10,000 stars.
我们知道有数以千计的其他各类小星团
We know of thousands of those kinds of smaller clusters.
现在 我们只知道有十来个大星团
Right now, we only know of a dozen of the massive clusters.
因为我们的星系里充满了尘埃
Because our galaxy is so filled with dust,
所以迄今所发现的大多数星团都存在于一个区域
most star clusters discovered so far exist in an area
围绕着我们银河系的一个特定的地方
surrounding our particular place in the Milky Way.
我们几乎无法看到银河系的中心
We can see barely as far as the center of the galaxy.
不过随着技术的提高
But as technology improves,
我们的视野深入得越来越远
our view will extend further and further
进入了更远的旋臂
into the more distant spiral arms.
韦斯特伦德1将不会长期是已知最大的年轻星团
Westerlund 1 won't be the most massive young cluster known for a long time.
我们一直不断地发现其它的这类星团
We're still discovering these other clusters all the time.
少数超级星团就在星系中心附近
A few superclusters are near the galactic core
银河系巨大的黑洞的引力潮汐
where the gravitational tides of the Milky Way's giant black hole
会在短短的几百万年里将它们撕碎
may rip them apart in just a few million years.
不过现在 其中巨大的亮星
For now though, their massive bright stars
正被紧锣密鼓地研究
are being studied intensely.
我们的下一站是五胞胎星团
Our next stop is the Quintuplet Cluster,
一个巨大的400万岁的星团
a massive 4-million-year-old cluster
因盘踞在其中心的五颗超级巨星而得名
named for five supergiants dominating its center.
它也是手枪星的老巢
It is also home to the Pistol Star,
它是整个星系里最亮的恒星之一
one of the brightest stars in the entire galaxy.
星团有五颗神秘的超级巨星
The cluster has five mysterious supergiants
其神秘之处在于笼罩在红色的尘埃云里
whose secrets are shrouded by red dust clouds.
2006年 困惑的科学家试图仔细观察它们
In 2006, puzzled scientists tried to get a closer look at them
用上了夏威夷的凯克望远镜
using the Keck Telescope in Hawaii.
他们发现的东西让人吃惊
What they found was startling.
其中的两颗星周围有怪异的螺旋
Two of the stars are surrounded by bizarre spirals,
这意味着超级巨星并不孤单
which means the supergiants are not alone.
在五胞胎星团里 有几颗大质量恒星
In the Quintuplet star cluster, there are several massive stars
实际上是双星系统
that are, in fact, in binary systems,
它们正温柔地将自己的外壳吹走
and they're in the process of gently blowing away their outer envelopes,
那些外壳不断碰撞 形成了螺旋形状
and those envelopes are colliding and forming the spiral pattern.
在同一个地方发现有几个这样的东西非常罕见
It's very unusual to find several of these things in the same place.
这样的恒星十分罕见
Such stars are very rare.
你看我们星系的其他地方
If you look elsewhere in our galaxy,
会发现每一个都是零星分布一段时间
you'll find one every once in a while here and there,
不会有几个集中在一个地方的
but not several of them in one concentrated location.
这不仅关乎这之前的时间
It's only a matter of time before these
而且上百颗其它大质量恒星中的任何一颗
and any of a hundred other super massive stars
以超新星爆发点亮了星团
light up the cluster with supernova explosions,
吹走了它们自己的行星 用致命的辐射
blowing away their own planets and wiping out any civilizations
抹去了邻近世界里的所有文明
on neighboring worlds with deadly radiation.
类似的威胁潜伏在另一个星团里面
Similar dangers lurk inside another cluster
它靠近星系的中心
close to the galactic center.
它就是圆拱星团 距离地球2 5万光年
It's called the Arches Cluster, 25,000 light-years from Earth
距离银河系的中心就100光年
and just 100 light-years from the Milky Way's core.
圆拱星团是银河系里发现的首个年轻大星团
The Arches Cluster was the first young massive cluster discovered in the galaxy.
它是星系中最致密的年轻星团
It is the densest young cluster in the galaxy.
我们太阳所在的街区相对圆拱星团来说
Our own Sun's neighborhood is practically empty
几乎是空无一物
compared to the Arches Cluster.
在太阳周围的50立方光年里
In the 50 cubic light-years around the Sun,
唯一的邻居就是半人马座阿尔法星系
the only neighbor is the Alpha Centauri system.
如果我们是在圆拱星团里 恒星就拥挤在一起
If we were in the Arches Cluster, the stars are so tightly packed,
同样的空间里就会包含100多万颗恒星
this same space would contain more than a million stars,
照亮每一颗行星的天空 不分昼夜
lighting up the sky of any planet, both in night and day.
如果我们居住的行星所围绕的恒星是在圆拱星团
If we lived on a planet surrounding a star in the Arches Cluster
或类似稠密的星团里
or a cluster that's similarly dense,
我们就会在夜空里看到成千上万颗恒星
we'd see thousands of stars in the night sky.
事实上 其中的一些恒星将非常明亮
In fact, some of those stars would be so bright
它们各个都要比满月亮很多
that they would individually be much brighter than the full Moon.
夜空将非常明亮
The night sky would be very bright.
将相当于白天办公室里的光照水平
It would be comparable to the light level in an office during the day.
圆拱星团是我们星系的重要里程碑
The Arches Cluster is a major landmark in our galaxy
因为它被科学家用来
because it was used by scientists
了解恒星可以变得多大
to figure out just how big a star can get.
我们的搜索宇宙星团之旅已经将我们带到了圆拱星团
Our search for cosmic clusters has taken us to the Arches,
我们星系中最重要的星团之一
one of the most important clusters in our galaxy.
就是在这里 科学家发现了恒星可以变得有多大
It's here that scientists discovered just how massive a star can get.
那似乎是一个简单的问题
That seems like a simple question,
但我们直到几年前还不知道
but we didn't know up until a few years ago
恒星实际上可以变得有多大
how massive a star could actually be.
圆拱星团拥有科学家回答这个问题
The Arches had everything scientists needed
所需要的一切
to answer this question.
首先 在这么大的星团里
First, in such a big cluster,
肯定存在着许多大质量恒星供研究
there were surely many massive stars to study.
其次 大约250万岁
Second, at roughly 2 1/2 million years old,
星团非常年轻
the cluster was young enough
其大质量恒星尚未爆发
that its massive stars wouldn't have exploded yet.
因此星团中最大的恒星有可能对于
So the biggest star in the cluster would probably be a good guide
更广泛的宇宙间获得大质量恒星是一个很好的导向
for how massive stars could get in the wider universe.
我们在圆拱星团里所看到的是
What we saw in the Arches
集中了N多低质量的恒星
is a collection of many, many low-mass stars,
为数不多的 或许就是数百颗中等规模的恒星
not so many, maybe hundreds of medium-size stars,
以及十来颗质量是
and then a dozen or so very massive stars with
太阳130倍的大质量恒星
130 times the mass of the Sun in them.
除此之外 什么都没有了
Beyond that, we saw nothing.
就像是跌下了悬崖一样
It was like falling off a cliff.
如果有质量超过130个太阳的恒星可以形成并存在
If stars more massive than about 130 solar masses can form and live,
那么它们会一直呆在圆拱星团里
then they would have been there in the Arches,
因此很明显 大自然已安排了恒星质量的最大极限
so apparently nature has placed a limit on the maximum mass of a star.
它可能介于130到150个太阳质量之间
It's probably somewhere between 130 and 150 solar masses.
随着我们远离年轻的圆拱星团
As we travel away from the very young Arches Cluster,
我们安排了对星系完全不同的部分的行程
we chart a course for a very different part of the galaxy.
呆在银河系僻静的郊外的
Out in the Milky Way's quiet suburbs
是年长的公民 球状星团
are its senior citizens, the globular clusters.
球状星团听上去很美妙
A globular cluster sounds so wonderful.
它是我最中意的世界之一 球状
It's one of my favorite words, a glob,
确实是那回事
and that's exactly what it is,
往往有上百万颗恒星挤在一个大星团里
often up to a million stars in a tight, large cluster.
那些东西确实很神秘
These things are really mysterious
因为它们看上去都很老了
because they seem to be very old,
一些星系里最古老的恒星
some of the oldest stars in the galaxy.
事实上 有些恒星非常古老
In fact some of the stars are so old,
几乎与宇宙本身一样的年纪
they're practically as old as the universe itself.
虽然它们看上去很漂亮
Though they are visually stunning,
但是令人兴奋的是球状星团的年纪
it's the age of the globular clusters that makes them so exciting.
由于它们几乎与宇宙本身一样古老
Since they are nearly as old as the universe itself,
所以它们就涉及了星系年龄的问题了
they raise the question of the galaxy's age.
银河系是否也和宇宙一般古老呢？
Is the Milky Way as ancient as the universe itself?
我们已很好地证明了宇宙
We have good evidence that the universe
约137亿岁了
is about 13.7 billion years old.
鉴于最老的球状星团约130亿岁
Given that the oldest globular clusters are about 13 billion years old,
这就意味着它们形成于大爆炸后的最早的10亿年里
this means that they formed within the first billion years after the Big Bang.
这基本上标志着我们星系的诞生
This essentially marks the birth of our galaxy,
我们认为其它星系也是
and we think other galaxies as well,
在许多案例里 形成于宇宙诞生后的
in many cases, were formed within the first billion years
最早的10亿年里
after the birth of the universe.
科学家不知道球状星团是如何形成的
Scientists don't know how globular clusters form.
它是当今天文学的一大谜团
It's one of today's enduring mysteries of astronomy.
因为它们在其它星系里也有所发现
Because they are found in other galaxies too,
因此它有可能牵涉到星系本身的形成
it may have something to do with galaxy formation itself.
因为我们看到球状星团里个别恒星非常古老
Because we see that individual stars in globular clusters are very old,
某种案例里已记录到有130亿岁
in some cases being dated to 13 billion years old,
我们知道球状星团有这么老了
we know that the globulars are that old,
我们知道它们的形成
and we know that they were formed
就在星系的形成时
right at the time when the galaxy was forming.
目前尚不清楚究竟是系统形成在先
It's still unclear whether the system formed first
然后是星系在残留的分子云里凝聚而成的呢
and then the galaxy condensed out of the remaining molecular cloud,
还是它们凝聚 塌缩 同时形成的呢
or if they condensed and collapsed and formed at the same time.
寻找球状星团
Finding globular clusters
把我们带出了混沌的星系盘
takes us outside the chaotic disk of the galaxy,
那里是大部分恒星的住所
where most of the stars reside,
来到的地方叫做星系晕
and to a place called the galactic halo.
我们银河系的晕
The halo of our Milky Way Galaxy
是周围恒星的广袤近乎球状的分布地
is a vast, roughly spherically shaped distribution of stars that's around,
它笼罩着我们的螺旋星系盘
it envelops the disk of our spiral galaxy.
是球状星团的居住地
It's where the globular clusters live.
目前已知有约160个球状星团
There are about 160 globular clusters now known,
但是相信曾经有过更多
but it's believed there were once many more of them.
它们出现在晕里 超出了星系盘的影响
Their presence in the halo, outside the influence of the galactic disk,
可能由此它们保持了球状
may figure into the way they keep their spherical form.
有可能所有的球状星团都是在早就消散的星盘附近
It may be that any globulars near the disk dissipated long ago.
但是至少有一个星团置身晕的外面
But there's at least one cluster out in the halo
处在被撕裂的险境之中
that's in danger of being ripped apart,
星团已经丢失了它最早形成时的八成的恒星
a cluster that has lost 80% of the stars it had when it was first formed.
我们安排行程去球状星团M12
We set our course for globular cluster M12
近距离观察破坏的情景
to get an up-close view of the devastation.
M12 并不是运行在我们星系的外面
M12, instead of orbiting outside of our galaxy
或穿行在外边缘
or going through the outer edges,
而是实际上是穿行在我们星系的中心附近
actually passed close to the center of our galaxy.
这样一来 与银河系内部的其它恒星的引力互动
And when it did that, the gravitational interaction with all the other stars inside the Milky Way
强烈到足以将星团里的一些低质量的恒星拉走
was strong enough to pull off some of the low-mass stars inside the cluster.
因此情况就是M12在每一次经过我们星系时
So what's happening is that M12 is slowly losing its lowest-mass stars
慢慢丢失其低质量恒星
with every successive passage through our galaxy,
最终将不会有任何东西留下
and eventually there's not going to be anything left
因为它将被银河系给完全吞噬
because it will have been completely devoured by the Milky Way.
眼下 大多数星团仍然非常拥挤
For now, most globular clusters remain very crowded,
密度是我们所在星系街坊的6万倍
60,000 times as dense in stars as our own galactic neighborhood.
然而因为星团都很年长了
But because the clusters are old,
因此所有的大质量恒星早已精疲力尽了
any massive bright stars they once had have long since burned out.
球状星团里非常拥挤
The globular cluster sky would be crowded,
但是其光辉将奄奄一息
but its glow would remain subtle.
如果我们在球状星团的一颗恒星的行星上
If we were on a planet around a star in a globular cluster,
会看到有成千上万颗恒星
we would see thousands of stars,
但是夜间的平均亮度就相当于
but the average illumination at night would be comparable to
你在有几根蜡烛的房间里的亮度
the illumination you'd experience in a room with some candles lit up.
运行在晕的外面 球状星团对于星系而言
Orbiting out in the halo, globular clusters are to the galaxy
某种程度就像是卫星围绕着行星
something like moons are to a planet.
其它星系外围的球状星团
Globular clusters on the outskirts of other galaxies
表明了这是许多星系的共同之处
show that this is something many galaxies have in common.
现在我们的太空之旅带我们远离我们的星系
Now our route through space takes us far outside our own galaxy,
6000万光年之外
60 million light-years away,
去一个巨大的椭圆星系 - M87
to a massive elliptical galaxy called M87
看上去本身就像是球状星团
that looks something like a globular cluster itself.
哈勃太空望远镜的这张照片中的多数模糊点
Most of the fuzzy dots in this photo from the Hubble Space Telescope
就是围绕着M87的球状星团
are globular clusters orbiting M87.
大星系里有15000个星团
The giant galaxy has 15,000 of them.
不过M87代表了积聚现象的高位
But M87 represents the upper end of the clustering phenomenon.
位居星团核心的 不是恒星
It sits at the core of a cluster, not of stars,
而是星系 我们的飞船现在所到之处
but of galaxies where our starship now travels
见证了巨大星系的暴戾
to witness the violence of giant star systems
正在以时速上百万英里碰撞
colliding at speeds of a million miles an hour.
匆匆一览星团整个看到的是
All it takes is a few quick looks at star clusters
引力在把群星结合在一起的作用有多明显
to see how obvious gravity's effect is in holding stars together.
引力就像是宇宙间的雕塑家
Gravity is like the sculptor of the universe.
它影响了周围的大片区域
It influences large regions around it.
因此它可以导致星系簇拥在一起
So it can cause galaxies to cluster together
就像群星簇拥在一起一样 不过那是在大N多倍的规模上
just like stars cluster together, but on a much, much bigger scale,
在数百万光年的规模上
on scales of millions of light-years.
真是难以置信
That's fantastic.
那个过程就开始在我们的天文后院
It's a process that begins right in our own astronomical backyard,
就是我们的飞船行将飞出银河系的地方
where our spaceship prepares to fly outside the galaxy.
银河系可谓很大了 不过相对典型的螺旋星系
The Milky Way is a largish but relatively typical spiral galaxy,
我们位于一个不大的星系群里
and we're located in a small galaxy group,
这对置于宇宙中的材料来说
which is a very typical kind of environment
是一种非常典型的环境
for material to be located in in the universe.
只有5%的星系座落在富星系团里
Only about 5% of galaxies are located in rich clusters,
但是其中超过一半都位于小星系群里
but more than half of them are located in small groups of galaxies.
我们银河系所在的星系团叫做本星系群
Our galaxy's home cluster is called the Local Group.
跨越300万光年的行程带我们越过了它的两个大成员
A trip across 3 million light-years takes us past its two big members,
银河系和M31 - 仙女座星系
the Milky Way and M31, the Andromeda Galaxy.
三角座星系是次大的
The Triangulum Galaxy is the next largest,
几十个矮星系在其中穿越
and a few dozen dwarf galaxies circulate among them.
单个星系群里的星系
The galaxies within an individual cluster
往往会随着时间的推移逐步合并在一起
tend to gradually merge with time,
因此在接下来的40 50 60亿年里 我们的银河系
so in the next 4, 5, 6 billion years, our Milky Way Galaxy
将会与仙女座星系合并在一起
is going to merge with the Andromeda Galaxy.
现在 如果我们在地球轨道上看整个宇宙
Right now, if we view the whole universe from Earth orbit,
我们的银屏上就是这个样子
our view screen looks like this.
我们的星系水平居中 从中向两头延展
Our own galaxy's plane dominates, stretching across the center.
但是一旦我们与仙女座星系合并后
But when we merge with Andromeda,
天空看上去将会有巨大的改变
the sky will look vastly changed.
一个非常壮观的事件
A very spectacular event,
有可能会导致一个椭圆星系
it's likely to result in an elliptical galaxy
看上去就完全不同于这两个螺旋星系中的任何一个
which looks very, very different than either of the two component spirals.
仙女座会掠过几回
Andromeda will fly by several times
与银河系一道跳起引力舞蹈
as it and the Milky Way do a gravitational dance.
合并将破坏它们优雅的碟状
The merger will destroy their elegant disk shapes.
最后 它们将定型为一个巨大的球状
In the end, they'll settle into a giant rounded blob,
宇宙间椭圆星系的典型形状
the typical form of elliptical galaxies across the universe.
本星系群相比宇宙中的大星系团来说是很小的
The Local Group is tiny compared to the big galaxy clusters across the universe.
最近的大星系团是我们行程的下一站
The nearest big cluster is the next stop on our voyage.
我们的本星系群6000万光年外
Our Local Group is about 60 million light-years away
是一个大N多倍的星系团 - 室女座星系团
from a much bigger cluster, the Virgo cluster of galaxies,
包含有成千上万个星系 不只是几十个
consisting of thousands of galaxies, not just a few dozen.
我们本星系群和室女座星系团
And our Local Group and the Virgo Cluster
以及一群其他星系团
and a bunch of other clusters
构成了一个更大的结构 叫做本超星系团
are part of an even bigger structure called the Local Supercluster.
这些星系团都是狂暴之地
Such clusters are violent places
星系的移动速度惊人
with galaxies moving at incredible speed.
我们说道的速度是每秒数百公里
We're talking about speeds of hundreds of kilometers per second,
换句话说就是
or another way of saying that would be
时速接近百万英里
something in the vicinity of a million miles an hour.
我们的行程进入了这些巨大星系团的高速王国
We take our trip into the high-velocity realm of these giant clusters
来解决星系的一个谜团 -
to solve a mystery about galaxies--
为何有些有恒星在星团里形成 而有些则没有
why some have stars forming in clusters and others don't.
答案就存在于星系的气体里
The answer is found in galactic gas.
星系或有气体丰富的 或有气体匮乏的
Galaxies are sometimes gas-rich and sometimes gas-poor.
气体丰富的往往形成恒星相当积极
Gas-rich galaxies tend to be forming stars fairly actively,
而气体匮乏的则不行了
and the gas-poor ones don't.
原来星系团里的活动
It turns out that the action in galaxy clusters
就像是战场 那里的百万英里的时速
is something like a war zone, where the million-mile-an-hour speeds
将任何气体丰富的星系置于被扼杀的险境
put any gas-rich galaxy in danger of being strangled.
星系的扼杀发生就在星系还不属于星系团
Galaxy strangulation occurs when a galaxy that's not part of a cluster
靠近星系团时
comes close to a cluster,
引力的拉扯 星系团的潮汐拉力
and the gravitational pull, the tidal pull of that cluster,
会拿走或吸掉新来的星系里的气体
can remove or suck gas out of that incoming galaxy.
那就使得星系气体匮乏
That leaves the galaxy deficient in gas,
因而就无法形成更多的新恒星
and so it's unable to form many new stars.
它遭到了扼杀
It gets strangled.
一旦星系走到星系团的深处
And once a galaxy travels deep inside the cluster,
它所面临的麻烦叫做撞击压力剥离
it faces trouble from what's called ram pressure stripping
此时它快速通过漂浮在星系团空间里的薄薄的气体
as it speeds through the thin gas floating in the cluster space.
急速穿过那气体时
When zooming through that gas,
气体的压力实际上会将气体
the pressure of the gas can actually strip gas
从星系本身剥离 使其相对缺乏气体
away from the galaxy itself, leaving it relatively gas-free
无法形成较多的新的星团
and unable to form many new star clusters.
如果我们飞过星团 寻找星际气体
If we flew through the cluster, looking for the intergalactic gas,
会一无所获的
we wouldn't see it.
它实在是非常稀薄 我们会认为完全是真空
It is so very thin that on Earth, we'd consider it a perfect vacuum.
但要是我们打开飞船上的X射线探测器
But if we turn on our spaceship's x-ray detectors,
就会显示出大量可怕的光辉
it would show up as a massive eerie glow.
我们在可见光里看到的星系
The galaxies that we see in visible light,
如果我们用普通望远镜看的话
if we look with an ordinary telescope,
并不是星系团里唯一的成分
aren't the only component of galaxy clusters.
事实上 它们甚至都不是主要的成分
Indeed, they're not even really the dominant component.
主要成分是高温的稀薄的气体
The dominant component is a hot, thin gas.
气体的冲击加热
And the gas was heated by shocks
来自星团的形成过程中
during the formation process of the clusters
现在温度极高 发出了X射线
and is now so hot that it glows in x-rays.
这是完全看不见 不同于普通光
And this is completely invisible to normal light.
热气体对星团施加的引力影响
The hot gas exerts more gravitational influence
大大超过看得见的星系本身
on the cluster than the visible galaxies themselves.
其势不可挡的引力
Its overwhelming gravity
有助于将星团里的星系拉在一起形成一个共同的中心
helps draw cluster galaxies to a common center,
我们观察星系团时
and when we look at galaxy clusters,
看到了我们自己未来的预展
we see a preview of our own future.
星系团的中心往往是一个巨大的椭圆星系
In the cluster's center is often a giant elliptical galaxy,
是无数引力驱动的合并的结果
the result of countless gravity-driven mergers,
比如银河系与仙女座的合并
like the one that will join the Milky Way with Andromeda.
那是星系团的普遍趋势
That's a common trend for clusters of galaxies.
其中的星系不断合并在一起
The galaxies within them are merging together,
形成少量 最后是一个超星系团
forming a few, and finally one supergalaxy.
宇宙是不是注定要充斥孤单的超星系团呢？
Is the universe destined to be filled with isolated supergalaxies?
引力会不会继续无休止地拉扯呢？
Will gravity continue its unending pull?
为了找到答案
To find the answers,
我们请出超级计算机来作为时间机器
we enlist supercomputers as time machines,
把我们带入未来
taking us into the future.
它们所预测的情景
The scenario they predict
其严酷可能远远超出所有人的怀疑
may be far more grim than anyone ever suspected.
世界上最大的望远镜和卫星观察站
The world's greatest telescopes and satellite observatories
日复一日地提供着精彩的宇宙星团照片
routinely serve up awesome pictures of cosmic clusters.
但是基本上这些都只是一次性快照
But essentially these are only snapshots in time.
为了真实地观察宇宙的演化
To truly watch the universe as it evolves,
我们就需要有时间机器
we need a time machine.
人类生命相对宇宙的时间尺度来说如白马过隙
Human lives are short compared with cosmic time scales,
但是我们能够有效地观察到星系及星系团是如何演化的
but we can watch effectively how galaxies and galaxy clusters evolve
依靠强大的计算机来模拟它们
by simulating them on powerful computers.
超级计算机把我们的星际飞船变成了时间机器
The supercomputer turns our starship into a time machine
用于我们的下一段任务
for the next leg of our mission,
去了解宇宙的演化
to find out how the universe evolved
以及它最终的情况
and where it's going to end up.
这种模拟演示了星系团是如何形成的
This simulation shows how a galaxy cluster may form.
123亿年的星际演化
12.3 billion years of stellar evolution
浓缩成了不到一分钟
is condensed into less than a minute.
这样的超级计算机的可视化是重要的手段
Supercomputer visualizations like these are important tools
帮助我们大家了解宇宙的运作
to help all of us understand the workings of the universe
以及未来会将我们带向何处
and where the future will take us.
我们如何实际模拟出
The simulations where we can actually play
星系团在数十亿年里的演化
how a galaxy cluster evolves over billions of years
一直都是我的心病
always leave me breathless.
看到宇宙时间表演在这些美丽优雅的模拟中
It's amazing to watch cosmological time
让人叹为观止
play in these beautiful, elegant simulations.
这就是超级计算机的运作情况
Here's how the supercomputers do it.
它们开始于某种东西
They start with something
科学家将其称之为N体问题(N-body problem)
that scientists call the N-body problem.
N表示天体的数量
"N" stands for number of bodies.
天体就是行星 恒星 或星系
The bodies are planets, stars, or galaxies,
问题是通过一些简单的计算
and the problem is to do some simple math
来计算出牛顿的基本引力定律是如何
to figure out how Isaac Newton's basic laws of gravity
让行星或恒星在太空中运动的
make the planets or stars move in space.
这种模拟是极其强有力的手段
Such simulations are remarkably powerful ways
来研究复杂系统 如星系团
to study how complex systems like clusters of galaxies
及星系是如何与时俱进的
and galaxies evolve with time.
彼得 图本 - 马里兰大学的模拟专家
Peter Teuben, a simulation specialist at the University of Maryland,
将引力公式编程
programs the gravity formulas
到了一台叫做沉思的计算机里
into a supercomputer named Deepthought.
很容易 比如
It's easy, for instance,
要计算出行星围绕恒星的轨道
to figure the orbit of a planet around a star.
这叫做二体问题
That's called a two-body problem.
大学数学系学生立刻就可以解决
A college math student can do it in a snap.
不过想想你要计算星团里一大堆恒星的运动呢
But suppose you have to work out the motions of a swarm of stars in a star cluster.
N体问题有点像杂耍表演
The N-body problem is a little bit like a juggling act.
如果你碰上二体问题 我们这里有一个球
If you have a two-body problem, here we have one ball
我玩一个球相对比较容易 但是我不是杂耍家
I can do one ball relatively easy, but I'm not a juggler.
我不知道我能不能玩两个球 哎呀
I don't know if I can do two balls. Oops.
啊 显然 我玩不了两个球
Well, clearly, I cannot do two balls.
需要大量的尝试和大脑的演绎
And it takes a lot of effort and interpretation by the brain
如何来正确地杂耍这两个球
how to correctly juggle two balls.
现在来设想我们要来玩三个球或四个球
Now imagine that we have to do three balls or four balls.
我可来不了
I cannot do that.
有人能做到的
There are people who can do that.
不过复杂性会止于某个点上
But the complexity ends at some point.
没人能玩到20个球
Nobody can do 20 balls.
出人意料的是 问题背后的数学却是相当简单的
Surprisingly, the math behind the problem is fairly easy,
但是你需要超级计算机的原因就在于
but the reason you need a supercomputer
只有它能够做到这么多
is that there's just so much of it to do.
这纯粹是枯燥的工作
It's pure grunt work
好 伙计们 写上你的位置
All right, guys, write your positions.
来看图本学生的论证
As Teuben's students demonstrate,
试图不用计算机来解决12颗恒星
when trying to do it for 12 stars without a computer.
第一颗在6-4
Number 1 is at 6-4.
第二 在3-4
- Number 2. - 2 is at 3-4.
第三 在2-4
- Number 3. - 3 is at 2-4.
在这样的计算中
In calculations like these,
每颗星的初始位置在图标上都有了坐标
each star's starting position gets coordinates on a chart.
第八在4-4
Number 8 is at 4-4.
每颗星同时有了自己的速度
Each star also gets its own speed,
剩下的事就取决于同学们了
and the rest is up to the students.
利用牛顿定律 他们要计算出
Using Newton's laws, they have to figure out
每颗星的引力是如何与其它每颗星的作用
how each star's gravity acts on each one of the others
来确定每颗星在下一个时间点的具体位置
to determine where each star's position will be at the next point in time.
第一颗
Number 1.
这些同学将需要不间断工作300年
These students would need to work for 300 years nonstop
来完成超级计算机一秒钟所做的工作
to do what a supercomputer can do in one second.
星系团的计算将猛增到数以百万计
Calculations for galaxy clusters ramp up to millions,
甚至数十亿个N体
even billions of "N" bodies.
但是幸运的是 超级计算机越来越能够满足
But fortunately, supercomputers are increasingly available
天文学家模拟宇宙的过去 现在和将来的渴望
to astronomers eager to simulate the past, present, and future of the universe.
目前最先进的超级计算机
The current state-of-the-art supercomputers
实际上都是现成的计算机
are actually off-the-shelf computers
你我家用的台式计算机
that you and I use at home, desktop computers.
唯一的事情就是我们将它们组合在一起
The only thing is we put them all together.
它们不难建起 并不昂贵
They're easy to build, they're cheap to build,
因此可以用上好多
so there's many available.
最复杂的趋势模拟之一
Among the most complex of the current simulations
是欧洲的千年运算
is the Millennium Run in Europe,
100亿个星系的运算 靠一台超级计算机
where 10 billion galaxies were manipulated in a supercomputer,
连续运算20天 用了34 3万处理器时
running continuously for 28 days, utilizing 343,000 processor-hours.
其中一项成果是引人注目的3D飞行
One result is a remarkable 3-D fly-through
跨越240光年的空间
across 2.4 billion light-years of space,
演示了数亿个星系
showing hundreds of millions of galaxies
沿着无数股暗物质团聚成星团
clumped together in clusters along vast strands of dark matter.
利用超级计算机 科学家不仅能研究过去
Using supercomputers, scientists not only study the past,
而且还能预测宇宙的未来
but they can predict the future of the universe.
我认为真是酷毙了
I think it's amazingly cool that
我们实际上能够用上我们所知的宇宙当今的环境
we can actually take what we know about the present-day conditions in the universe
我们基本上能够利用这些计算机模拟
and we can basically use these computer simulations
来演示时间的推进
to play time forward.
我们能够利用这个来推断最终发生在我们身上的情况
We can use this to extrapolate what's going to happen to us in the end.
这个模拟开始于大爆炸留下的量子泡沫
This simulation starts with the quantum foam left over from the Big Bang
让我们穿梭130亿年
and flies us through 13 billion years
伴随它沿着网状的脉络和空隙
as it all condenses into the galaxy clusters and superclusters
整个凝结成星系团和超星系团
along the network of filaments and voids
就像那些我们今天所能发现的
like those we can detect today.
这就是宇宙团聚现象
This is the cosmic clustering phenomenon
有引力驱动到最大极限
driven by gravity to its greatest extreme.
但是引力的牵引被神秘的暗能量给抵消了
But gravity's pull is counterbalanced by the mysterious dark energy
它正在把宇宙间的星系团驱散
that is driving the galaxy clusters of the universe apart.
约10年前 天文学家发现了
About a decade ago, astronomers discovered
宇宙不光在膨胀
that the universe is not just expanding.
事实上 膨胀正愈演愈快
In fact, its expansion is accelerating with time.
引力将星系团结合在一块只是在局部层面上
Gravity will keep galaxy clusters together only on a local level.
我们的本星系群将会合并为一个超星系团
Our local galaxy group will coalesce into one supergalaxy,
但是宇宙间其他所有的星系将会快速远离我们
but all other galaxies in the universe will race away from us.
从今1000亿年后
A hundred billion years from now,
这个宇宙角落将暗无天日
this corner of space will be left virtually in the dark.
我们周围的遥远星系
As soon as the distant galaxies around us
将渐行渐远 达到光速
will expand away and reach the speed of light,
甚至它们发出的光线一点都永远无法到达我们这里
even light from them will never be able to reach us anymore,
因此这些星系将扩展成
and so these galaxies will expand
茫茫空域 并从视野中消失
into vast regions of space and disappear from view.
我们的星系将成为黑夜中的孤岛
Our galaxy will be an island embedded in darkness.
气体云将继续在附近形成星团
Clouds of gas will continue to form into star clusters nearby,
但是未来的天文学家将在我们星系的边界外的
but astronomers of the future will see nothing in the sky
天空中看不到任何东西
beyond the borders of our own galaxy.
除非今天的宇宙学家的工作得以保存
Unless the work of today's cosmologists is preserved,
否则将没有任何线索去告诉他们
there will be no clues to tell them
曾经有过一次大爆炸 有过宇宙膨胀
that there was once a Big Bang and a cosmic expansion,
将没有什么能让他们知道广阔天地
nothing to let them know of the vast existence
远不止这个空间 就是我们今天所谓的 - 宇宙
beyond the place we know today as The Universe.